# 好看
Beautiful
# 起来了
Get them up
# 今天想给大家做一个沙琪玛
Today I want to make Shaqima
# 点心里边我最爱吃的就是沙琪玛
Among all kinds of desserts, I love Shaqima the most
# 家里的很快就会学会
It is very easy to make at home, easy to learn
# 大大爷好
Dadaye hello
# 今天又请您过来了
Today we invited you again
# 受累受累
Sorry for the hassle
# 大热天的
And it is quite hot today
# 大大爷好好
Dadaye how are you
# 做的时候呢
To make Shaqima
# 我们要求175克的白糖
We need 175g of sugar
# 搁75克的蜂蜜
Prepare 75g of honey
# 这是咱们家做
We are making this at home
# 不像我们饭店有饴糖
Unlike in restaurants, we have caramel there
# 家里的条件有什么做什么
At home, we will use whatever we have
# 拿蜂蜜就解决了这个问题
Like honey will solve this caramel substitute problem
# 现在我们开始
Now let’s begin
# 做这个
To make this
# 半斤面
250g of flour
# 一般的三个到三个半鸡蛋就行了
Normally we need 3 to 3.5 of eggs
# 就全蛋面不加任何的水
It’s called egg noodles, we do not add any water
# 我们要求一斤面搁2.5克的泡打粉
We need to add 2.5g of baking powder into 500g of flour
# 这是半斤面
This is 250g of flour
# 我们要求用一半
We require to use half of it
# 和的时候
Now when we mix them together
# 一定要搅拌均匀
We need to mix them well
# 好哇这个
This looks nice
# 好吃啊
Taste good
# 当年老佛爷爱吃这个
At the time, queen loved this dessert
# 对
Yes
# 起满族传过来的
This originate from Manchu culture
# 非常好吃的沙琪玛
Very delicious Shaqima
# 揉成这样
Knead into this dough
# 还有点儿麻麻光光的
Not too smooth
# 饧发好了
Once rested
# 咱们再揉揉
We will knead again
# 就是饺子面那么软硬就行了
It will be ready when it feels like dumplings dough
# 这个面已经揉了两次
I kneaded this dough twice now
# 让它特别滋润了
It is very moist now
# 现在就可以开始擀了
Now we can roll out the dough
# 我们用的是玉米淀粉
Here we are using corn starch
# 光滑
Very smooth
# 不容易粘
Not very sticky
# 咱们平常跟家里擀面条一样就行
Roll the dough out like making noodles at home
# 是吧
Right
# 咱们半斤一会就炸出来不少
The 250g of flour can make a lot of Shaqima
# 出数
Efficient
# 家里头都能做
We can make it at home
# 看完了师傅做这个
Look at master making it
# 不是您要不教家里能做的
If you don’t teach us how to make it at home
# 我就认为在家里永远都做不了
I don’t ever think we can make it at home
# 没有什么难的
It is not that hard
# 这回我回家可以做
Now I can make it at home
# 这个呢薄厚都擀匀
We should try to make the thickness consistent
# 这个就是往前推 按
The technique is to push the dough forward, then press it
# 往外按
Press toward the edge
# 连按带推 对
Push then press, right
# 其实这个面谁都会擀
Actually, everyone can roll out the dough
# 但是擀出来效果都不一样
But the outcome will be very different
# 你看到没有擀的薄厚一致
You see the consistency of the thickness
# 这是要命的
This is really difficult
# 折完了之后 搁上薄面
After folding them, sprinkle some more starch
# 基本上都擀完了
Pretty much finish rolling the dough now
# 擀完了之后咱们就切
Now we can start cutting after rolling them out
# 咱们切成比韭菜还得细
We can cut it thinner than chives
# 面点也讲究刀工
Pastry chef needs to have good knife skills too
# 面条精细 粗细均匀
Think noodles and consistent width
# 这个弄完了之后呢
After cutting them
# 我们的要求这样
We still need to do this
# 把它打开
Spread them out
# 好了你看看
Now you see they are ready
# 一边齐 行了
Line them up, all good
# 这一会就开炸
Later on, we start frying
# 这个油温不能太热
The oil temperature cannot be to high
# 太热一下就炸糊了
If it is too high you might burn the noodles
# 要做的时候我们要求
While making it, we need to use
# 得有两个漏勺
Need to use 2 colanders
# 就是一下炸好了同一个颜色
We need to make sure all the noodles are fried to the same color
# 同时捞出来
Fish them out around the same time
# 一个漏勺
Using one colander
# 有时候捞的不均匀
Sometimes it might not be enough
# 底下就火大了
By the time you come back for the rest they are over fried
# (油温)3成到4成
(Oil temperature) 90-120 Celsius now
# 你看这个往里一搁 就起来了
You just put the noodles in, they will puff up immediately
# 油温不能太高
The oil temperature cannot be to high
# 一进去就出锅
Pretty much fishing them out right after putting them in
# 你瞧瞧这底儿这个不捞
You see if I don’t pick them up in time
# 颜色就不统一了
The color will be different
# 所以我们就拿俩漏勺
So, we are using 2 colanders
# 让它特别一致
To make the color consistent
# 弄完了跟爆米花似的
Once they are finished, they look quite like popcorn
# 不管炸几锅
It doesn’t matter how many noodles you are frying
# 这颜色都得一样
The color needs to be consistent
# 让它洁白让它酥
It’s white and crispy
# 你瞧瞧这个炸出来了
You see these fried noodles
# 半斤面你瞧瞧
This is from 250g of flour
# 就那么多了一大锅了
We fried such a big wok
# 这个呢传统的就用青红丝
Traditionally we use colored candy strips
# 现在有好些年轻人不喜欢青红丝的话
Now younger generations don’t like the colored candy strips
# 咱们可以买点儿果脯 红的绿的黄的
We can use the dry fruits, red green yellow fruits
# 切成小粒撒上
We chop them finely and sprinkle them on
# 也OK了
That’s okay too
# 我们把青红丝再揽两刀
Now we roughly cut the colored candy strips
# 不用那么长 为的点缀
We don’t need them to be that long, just garnish
# 开火
Turn on the stove
# 这个搁60克的水
We add 60g of water
# 搁175克的糖
Add 175g of sugar
# 我们熬糖稀
Now we are making syrup
# 小火熬着
Heating it with low heat
# 把这个糖充分熬化
Cook the sugar thoroughly and melt it
# 不能来回和了
You can keep mixing it
# 老和了一翻沙 就完蛋了
Mixing it too often will make crystalized sugar, then it doesn’t work
# 这特别烫 糖
This is very hot, the sugar
# 我们起边上沾一点
We get some sugar from the edge
# 这个没有丝
It doesn’t stretch
# 待一会就有丝了
Later on, you can stretch the syrup
# 汤汁也发亮了
When the syrup is shiny
# 对熬亮了
Yes, wait until it’s shiny
# 这时候呢
Now
# 我们把75克的蜂蜜倒进去
We are adding 75g of honey
# 小火熬着
Keep the low heat
# 这时候我回过来
Now I turn to the board
# 把案板上搁几粒芝麻 熟芝麻
Sprinkle some sesame onto the board, cooked sesame
# 这个基本上差不多了
Now it’s almost done
# 一定不能拿手指进去 进去就烫坏了
You can dip you finger in there, you might burn yourself
# 你看看这个
You see grab some from here
# 成丝了
You can stretch the syrup now
# 红了
It’s red
# 关上了 完了之后
Turn off the heat, once turning off the heat
# 你看这个啊我们均匀的撒上
You see we need to pour it over evenly
# 快点搅拌(不搅拌)成坨了
And mix them well quickly, otherwise it will stick together and hard to shape
# 均匀的搅拌
Mix them well
# 二伯您这责任可重大啊
Er Bai you have very important responsibility
# 嘿
Haha
# OK了
Okay
# 倒这上头就行了
You can pour them on this
# 嘿 真地道嘿
Ha, looks authentic
# 大概齐给它弄个长方形的
Shape it into a rectangular
# 型完了之后马上就要求成形
When you see the shape, you need to press it firm immediately
# 干净利落脆
Clean and quick
# 成型完了之后
When you see the shape
# 马上就开始压
Press it firm immediately
# 看看这个有多好
Look how nice it is
# 半斤面就能做那么多
250g of flour you can make this much
# 这时候青红丝点到为止
Now we just sprinkle some colored candy strips for decoration
# 完了之后呢 你看我们这个面特别光亮
Once done you see the noodles are very shiny
# 这时候我们最后把它再压一下
At the end, we press it a little bit
# 撒上芝麻的意思 你看看就是要不沾案子
The purpose of adding sesame is to avoid sticking to the board
# 有好多人呐都是一层芝麻
Many people add too many sesame seeds
# 不好吃
That wouldn’t taste good
# 没有必要
It’s not necessary
# 真漂亮
Very beautiful
# 嚯 瞧这声音
Wow, listen to the sounds
# 到口即化
It melts in your mouth
# 可以吃了可以了
Now it’s ready
# 二伯是吧 吃了一块又来一块
Er Bai, you see you are eating it like one after another
# 手里还捏一块
Have one on your hand
# 我吃了这是第7块了
This is my seventh piece
# 王师傅谢谢您
Thank you, Chef Wang,
# 确实辛苦
This is not easy
# 应该说
I should say
# 我是最爱吃沙琪玛
I love Shaqima the most
# 今天可以不夸张的说
I can say without exaggerating
# 绝对是不夸张实打实的说
Really honestly
# 是我一生当中吃沙琪玛最棒的一回
This is the best Shaqima I have ever had
# 过奖过奖
Thank you thank you
# 第一
First
# 就现在拿手捏着啊
Just when I hold it on my hand
# 有的人拿手捏着的
Some Shaqima when I am holding it
# 粘手
They are too sticky
# 另外搁嘴里酥脆
Your Shaqima is also crunchy when I eat it
# 不黏牙 有的还粘粘牙
But it doesn’t stick to my teeth, some other Shaqima stick to our teeth all the time
# 火候拿捏的好啊 熬糖的火候
The heat control is really good, the temperature to cook the syrup
# 熬糖是关键
The syrup is important
# 但是炸这面条更关键
But frying the noodles is more crucial
# 王师傅用那小锅
Chef Wang was using that little wok
# 用两把勺子同时出
And two colanders the same time
# 当时我还产生一种怀疑
I was suspecting
# 因为什么呢 两把勺 一把勺不能出啊
What was I suspecting, two colanders, why can’t you just use one colander?
# 所以说掌握这细节特别重要
So, I say that attention to details is very important
# 两把勺同时出颜色一致
Using two colanders to make sure the consistent color on fried noodles
# 所以王师傅在重要环节上
So, Chef Wang puts great attention to details
# 掌握的每一分每一秒每一刻非常的经典
In every step of the process
# 最后拌糖炒糖
At the end when you cook the syrup or mixing it with the noodles
# 是吧
Right
# 这糖炒到沾手出丝
Cook the syrup until it stretches
# 这个细节
The detail
# 从来以前我没了解过 今天我了解了
I never learned about this, but today I did
# 我给我们大大爷
I going to give our Dadaye
# 点个赞
A big praise
# 过奖过奖
Thank you thank you
# 真的 点个赞
Really, a big praise
# 看到我这小纸包了么
You see this little package
# 青红丝拿到手了
I got the colored candy strips
# 这礼拜六礼拜天回家做一个作业
This weekend I will go home and make it myself
# 向大大爷交一个作业
Submit the homework to Dadaye
# 我喜欢真的
I really like it
# 二伯说两句吧 我拍
Er Bay say something, I will film you
# 你把话都说完了
But you said them all
# 不是您精辟的总结性发言
Well you can have a summary
# 我就用这么最后一句话给结束
Okay I will end with the last sentence
# 你说一就一句了
Okay just one sentence
# 知道吧 就一句了吧
I know, just one sentence
# 你知道吗
You know
# 能工巧匠 巧夺天工
The great craftsmanship, is greater than nature
# 这就是我们心中的王师傅
This is our Chef Wang
# 就是我们心中的大大爷
This is our Dadaye
# 大爷跟二伯呢
Da ye and Er Bai
# 真的 都是夸奖我
Really this is all too much praise
# 其实也没有那么的好
It is not that great
# 所以就呈现给网友
Since we are showing the internet
# 一定要实话实说
We should tell it all
# 会了这种就能会好多种
Once you learn this one, you can make it into many different ones
# 还可以做成芙蓉糕
You can even make it into Furong Cake
# 还可以做成菊花沙琪玛
You can make Daisy Shaqima
# 所以希望网友们回去练一练
I hope you all practice it at home
# 我最担心的就是手指头杵在糖里头
I just worry that the syrup is very hot when you are testing it with finger
# 那就烫坏了
You might burn yourself
# 一定要有技巧
Really need to be careful and skillful with it
# 我们就想做的时候几个要领
Some key points I can think of are
# 刚才大爷都说了
Da ye said them all
# 和面的环节要好
You need to knead the dough well
# 我们能看见孔洞
So we can see holes
# 炸的颜色呢要统一要均匀
The fried noodles’ color needs to be consistent
# 为什么用俩漏勺呢 这都是细节的问题
Why do we need 2 colanders, it’s all about the details
# 再有就拍的时候
Then when you press it firm
# 不用拍的特别的紧
You don’t need to press too hard
# 也让他松一点
You can leave some space
# 撒果料的时候我也建议
When sprinkle the dry fruits
# 不要让它撒的都是 主要是点到为止
Don’t sprinkle too much on it, just a little bit
# 画龙点睛的事
For decoration
# 有些网友不喜欢青红丝
Some people don’t like colored candy strips
# 我劝大家可以买点果料
You can buy some dry fruits
# 是撒什么都行
Well you can add anything you like
# 让大家回去试一试
Everyone can try them at home
# 你看看我们就这点水
You see all we need is water
# 就这点糖
And some sugar
# 就这点蜂蜜
Some honey
# 正好就粘在这点面条
Wrap it around the fried noodles
# 所以我们想
So we think that
# 一定要不管做什么
Whatever you do
# 要做精做细才好
You need to make it very precise and detailed
# 对
Yes
# 谢谢大大爷 也谢谢大爷
Thank you Dadaye, and thank you Da ye
# 你知道这次最后我说一句话
You know this is my last sentence in the video
# 又一句啊
Another one?
# 老饭骨的精神就是什么啊
You know what Laofangu’s motto is?
# 匠心传承 绝不留遗憾
Passing on the traditional craftmanship heritage, never leave any regrets behind